<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons The angell guardian. The light enlightening. Preached by Iohn Bayly ...</title>
            <author>Bayly, John, 1595 or 6-1633.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836920</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836920</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1216</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1216)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 653:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons The angell guardian. The light enlightening. Preached by Iohn Bayly ...</title>
                  <author>Bayly, John, 1595 or 6-1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [3]; 14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield printer to the famous Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>a. D. 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>"The light enlightning" has separate dated title page, pagination and register. (Second title page is actually leaf C4 of first section.).</note>
                  <note>Only the first sermon appears on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1216:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1216:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS THE ANGELL <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARDIAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE LIGHT <hi>ENLIGHTNING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PREACHED BY IOHN BAYLY ONE OF HIS MAIESTIES CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAINES, <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARDIAN</hi> of Chrriſts Hoſpitall in <hi>Ruthyn,</hi> and ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Exeter Coll. Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
               <q>SA PI ET FELICI</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Litchfield, incorporating the arms of Oxford University (apparently not in McKerrow as such)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Lichfield</hi> Printer to the Famous Vniverſity, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1216:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1216:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, <hi>LEWES</hi> Lord Biſhop <hi>of Bangor.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Angell of God which hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to protected your Lordſhip from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moſt knowne and imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, tarry round about you and ſtill deliver you. I am the
<pb facs="tcp:1216:3"/>eldeſt ſonne of your body, this is the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt birth of my minde. By you I have beene conſecrated vnto Gods ſervice, and doe conſecrate this mine againe by you vnto his glory and the Churches good.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Chamber in Exon Coll. <date>Novemb. <hi>6.</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1630.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Sonne in all obedience to bee commanded. <hi>IOHN BAYLY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1216:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 34.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>The Angell of the Lord encampeth round about them that feare him and delivereth them.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all Gods Creatures man is the moſt excellent and noble. With things <hi>Inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate,</hi> we haue a <hi>being,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue them <hi>Sence,</hi> and aboue them <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mans nature by the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticall vnion with the ſecond perſon in the ſacred Trinitye is highly exalted aboue all principalityes and powers.</p>
            <p>In heauen we ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Angells.</hi> Here we doe, and there we ſhall ſerue God with them, but <hi>in via</hi> God hath ordayned them to ſerue vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.30.</note> 
               <hi>They are all ministring ſpiritts ordayned for their ſakes who are the elect of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is not improbable, that pride was the <hi>Angells.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1216:4"/>ſinne. And their ſinne was to refuſe this ſervice, not to adore the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> when that decree of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation</hi> was divulged, <hi>And let all the Angells of God adore him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In regard of this ſame communion an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Apoſtle calls it <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. (<hi>but Arith metice</hi> we are to vnderſtand it ſo, it is not <hi>rhetoricè,</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>coadvnationem vox denotat, Angelorum &amp; hominum veluti in vnam ſummam;</hi> as <hi>Cameron</hi> obſerues. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of this communion, we haue with the <hi>Angells</hi> here, and ſhall haue with them in the life to come here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, our Church doth yearely celebrate one day, <hi>this day</hi> that we may inſtruct, and the people may be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted concerning them.</p>
            <p>That we may then doe <hi>opus diei in die ſuo,</hi> the worke of the day vpon the day appointed for the worke; <hi>the text</hi> we are to intreate of, you ſhall finde <hi>pſal:</hi> 34.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Angell of the Lord encampeth &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein we doe obſerue, 1. <hi>That there is an Angell that doth protect vs,</hi> and that by an <hi>encamping round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs,</hi> not all in generall, but <hi>vs,</hi> that feare God, ſo the text is limited, They doe <hi>encampe</hi> themſelfes <hi>about thoſe that ſeare God</hi> and that ſecondly for their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and that is the end they ayme at in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Angell of the Lord encampeth &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Semper ſunt ſpiritus, non Angeli, ſed quando miſsi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: in Heb: and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Gr: doth ſignifie a <hi>meſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1.</note> and in this ſence our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lord of Angells is called the <hi>Angell of the Couenant</hi> in Malachi for he was <hi>Shilo miſſus a patre
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1216:4"/>ſent</hi> with authority as well to meritt as to <hi>preach</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation vnto men with God in him.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe the Miniſters of the word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſcripture are called <hi>Angells</hi> Math: 11.10. Rev. 1.20. for they are <hi>miſsi a filio, Ite in vniuerſum mundum, to them</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is committed the Miniſtrie of reconciliation</hi> merited by him.</p>
            <p>And againe <hi>know yee not</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.3.) <hi>that we ſhall Iudge the Angells,</hi> where by the <hi>Angells</hi> we vnderſtand the <hi>Diuills;</hi> for they are <hi>miſsi a Deo</hi> ſent of God to execute his judgment againſt the wicked, and for the probation or tryall alſo of the elect as in the ſtorie of Iob.</p>
            <p>Now to diſtinguiſh thoſe <hi>Angells</hi> of whom my text intreates from <hi>Men-Angells</hi> or miniſters as wee doe call them. They are ſaid to be <hi>ſpirits</hi> Heb: 1.7. <hi>he mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Angells ſpirits.</hi> And againe to diſtinguiſh them from Chriſt the Lord of <hi>Angells</hi> they are therefore ſaid to be <hi>made,</hi> or <hi>Created ſpirits:</hi> And to diſtinguiſh them from the <hi>Angells of darkeneſſe</hi> they are ſaid to be his <hi>Angells, Angells of light, Angells of God</hi> (in ſcrip:) <hi>by way of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie.</hi> The <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> it is my text doth ſpeake of, for ſoe the ſcripture doth vſually tearme all whatſoeuer is excellent to be of God, becauſe that all excellencie is from God.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Now in the generall of protecting Angells, we muſt needs ſpeake firſt <hi>of the diverſe orders or degrees</hi> of <hi>Angells,</hi> that in the ſecond place wee may know <hi>of what order or degree thoſe Angells are vnto whom this office of our protection is aſsigned.</hi> And then thirdly we ſhall enquire whether <hi>every one man hath his owne ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1216:5"/>Angell as a Custos or a Guardian Angell to protect him.</hi> And fourthly <hi>why it ſo pleaſed God to vſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of Angells</hi> when of himſelfe he is Almightie; and therefore able, and as willing as able to deliver them that feare him from danger; for he is moſt mercifull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto all thoſe that put their truſt in him. For the firſt you know how the ſchoolemen, led on by <hi>Dioniſius Areopagita</hi> who by <hi>Valla, Eraſmus,</hi> and all the learned world, is and was long ſince branded for a counterfeite, haue ſorted the whole heauenly ſociety of Angells into three Hierachies every Hierachie conteyning three orders and every order indefinite although not infinite numbers of Individuall ſpirits.</p>
            <p>The firſt Hierarchie is of <hi>Seraph: Cherub:</hi> &amp; <hi>Thrones.</hi> The ſecond of <hi>Dominations, principallities,</hi> and <hi>powers,</hi> the third of <hi>vertues, Arch-Angells, Angells.</hi> So that the 3 Hierarchies containe nine orders or ſpecies or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Angells. And that it is ſo they proue it thus.</p>
            <p>Diſtinct and diverſe names cannot but argue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and diſtinct orders, according to the number of names which in ſcripture are given vnto the <hi>Angells;</hi> but there are nine names only in ſcripture giuen vnto the <hi>Angells,</hi> therefore there can be no leſſe, nor may there be more then thoſe nine orders of <hi>Angells</hi> only, which you haue heard before recited.</p>
            <p>Wee will let the propoſition paſſe, but it is giuen, it is not granted,<note place="margin">Hieron. l. 2. adverſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>v. c. 15.</note> for all that, and it ſhall be giuen, becauſe as <hi>Hyerom:</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Sine cauſa eſt diverſitas nominum vbi non est diverſitas meritorum.</hi> It may ſeeme ſtrange that wee ſhould reade of <hi>Arch-Angells,</hi> if there bee no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1216:5"/>inferiour order or degree or ſort of <hi>Angells</hi> vnder them.</p>
            <p>But the aſſumption failes vtterly to inferre the exact number of nine only. For the <hi>Angells</hi> are moreover honored in ſcripture with the name of Elohim, and the <hi>ſonnes of God</hi> in regard of the neere Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion they haue with him. They are alſo called <hi>ſpirits</hi> as readie for to ſerue him. <hi>A flaming fire</hi> ardent to loue him,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.7. Heb. 1.7. Deut. 4.10.</note> and in regard of vs moreouer they are called watch-men, continually (as my text ſpeakes) <hi>encamping</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about vs.</p>
            <p>To this it's replied, that theſe we haue now laſtly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of are names in generall giuen vnto all the Angells. True, But is not the name of <hi>Angell</hi> it ſelfe a generall name? and why then ſhould they make a diſtinct order of <hi>Angells</hi> from the reſt?</p>
            <p>We doe not deny but that there are diverſe <hi>orders</hi> and <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>Angells,</hi> God is the God of <hi>order</hi> noe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> he doth not approve of <hi>ataxie.</hi> There is order among all the creatures of God, even in <hi>hell</hi> it ſelfe there is ſome <hi>vnrulye order,</hi> there is a Prince of darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>One ſtarre differreth from another in glorye. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.40. and there are diverſe manſions prepared for the, Elect in heauen, and yet the elect ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Angells</hi> be there.<note place="margin">Math. 22.3.</note> It is not therefore vnlike but that as the <hi>ſtarrs,</hi> and as the <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Angells</hi> may differ <hi>in menſura gloriae,</hi> among themſelues in degrees of glory, <hi>non gaudij</hi> though not of ioyes.</p>
            <p>But to define (as you heard the ſchoolemen doe) in particular wherein this ſame diverſitye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth as if they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1216:6"/>had come downe from heauen to tell men vpon earth what order was kept there; we ſay things ſecret belong vnto the Lord our God, but things revealed, only vnto vs. Or with Saint <hi>Hierome dicant qui poſſunt,</hi> lett them ſay it that can proue it I confeſſe I doe not know it. <hi>Boni Theologi eſt ſemper aliquid ignorare.</hi> This is <hi>ignorantia originaliter invincibilis</hi> and therefore not <hi>Culpabilis.</hi> Why is it <hi>Eſay.</hi> 6.2. that the Angells are there deſcribed thus, with one paire of wings they cover their faces, and with an other paire their feete? doubtleſſe to teach vs, that we <hi>in via</hi> are no way able to prye into the nature of the Angells, no nor the Angells <hi>in patria</hi> into the eſſence and nature of God, who as he is infinite may not be comprehended by them; they are finite. Difference there is of glory among the Angells, but what that difference is we know not, the ſchoolemen will tell you if they lye not; and further, of what order and degree thoſe Angells are, which (as my text ſpeakes) doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe themſelfes about vs. Which is the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> pointe we propoſed to intreate of.</p>
            <p>To this end they doe diſtinguiſh thoſe. 9. orders of Angells wee ſpeake of into 2. generall ſorts. Some they make of the <hi>privie Chamber,</hi> as it were, and ſome they place in the <hi>Lobbye</hi> ſome they tell vs are <hi>aſsistant,</hi> and ſome are <hi>ministring ſpirits. Aſsiſtant ſpirits</hi> are ſuch as doe continually reſide about and attend vpon the throne of God. <hi>Miniſtring</hi> ſpirits are ſuch as are ſent out or imployed on errands in the inferior world.</p>
            <p>Now the 4. firſt orders of <hi>ſeraph: Cher: throanes</hi> and <hi>dominations</hi> they ſtate to be <hi>aſsiſtant.</hi> The 5. later to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1216:6"/>be <hi>Miniſtring ſpirits.</hi> And yet I take it to be no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to ſay, That the ſame Angell, at the ſame time though not in the ſame reſpect, is both <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring</hi> and <hi>aſsistant</hi> too:<note place="margin">Greg. l. 2. Mor: c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>faciem patris ſemper vident</hi> for their <hi>aſsistancye &amp; tamen ad nos veniunt</hi> for their <hi>miniſtrye.</hi> But Saint <hi>Paule</hi> makes this a meere tale <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. Where he tells vs of the Angells, that they are all miniſtring ſpiritts. <hi>Omnes ſunt adminiſtratorii ſpiritus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ordina ſic literam</hi> ſayes <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> vpon that text,) reade it thus. They are all <hi>etiam de ſuperiori or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> of the higheſt degree <hi>ministring</hi> ſpirits ſent out and that <hi>miſſione exteriori</hi> a <hi>Cherub:</hi> it was that was ſett to keepe the way vnto the tree of life, and a <hi>ſeraphim</hi> it was who with a cole in his hand did ſome times touch the Prophets lippes. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Intelligere autem proprie debemus ea ſcripturae loca quae ſine incommodo ſic poſſunt intelligi,</hi> (it is S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> rule,) wee muſt vnderſtand what the ſcripture ſpeakes according to the letter of the text, if we find no plaine in convenience of contradiction vnto other places in it.<note place="margin">Gen: 3.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You haue heard then that there is no order of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells (Suppoſing that there be orders of Angells) exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted from <hi>encamping</hi> as my text ſpeakes, <hi>about them that feare God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing that wee are to intreate of is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be one <hi>Angell Guardian</hi> only or more aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to attend vs, <hi>pro ſingulis generum</hi> you muſt take it.</p>
            <p>The Platoniſts did teach (as I haue read in Proclus) that every man had three ſpecial Angells in this kind to attend vpon him.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1216:7"/>
            <p>The 1. was <hi>ſacer daemon</hi> and he had chargde over the reaſonable ſoule, to inſpire good thoughts and wholeſome councells, and to encline the will of them over whom their chardge was, to performe that which they did ſuggeſt for good.</p>
            <p>The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> was <hi>Genius.</hi> And he had chardge over the outward life to promote and further them vnto whom he was aſſigned towards the attaynement of that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune indefinitely good or bad vnto which as they ſpake, the borne was deſtinate. He therefore that had a good <hi>Genius</hi> was proverbially ſayd to be <hi>bene natus; Albae Galinae filius,</hi> happy and fortunate in all his actions.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> was <hi>ſpiritus Profeſsionis</hi> and his office it was to helpe and further men in their ſpeciall callings and trades of life. Hence it was that if the profeſſion which men betooke themſelves vnto, was alſo agreeing to the <hi>Genius</hi> of their nativity or birth, ſuch men (they taught) muſt needs be excellent and ſingular in what they did apply themſelues vnto, as having both their <hi>Genius</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, and their <hi>ſpiritus Profeſsionis</hi> to helpe them in it, <hi>vis vnita fortior.</hi> But if any man ſhould attempt a thing; <hi>Invita Minerva,</hi> contrarie vnto his <hi>Genius,</hi> doe his <hi>ſpiritus Profeſsionis</hi> the beſt it can, he ſhall never e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade rare or excellent therin.</p>
            <p>This I haue related, not that I doe aproue it, but that you may ſee, how that the heathen did know ingene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, although they erred in the particular Concerning this doctrine of <hi>Angellicall protection</hi> we are now to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of. <hi>Eſt Chorus Indigetum mortalibus additus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris,</hi> that we are protected by the Angells that is true,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1216:7"/>but whether by one or more that is queſtioned by more then one.</p>
            <p>For ſometimes in ſcripture wee reade of <hi>many</hi> Angells appointed vnto <hi>one</hi> man, ſometimes of <hi>one</hi> Angell vnto <hi>many</hi> men, &amp; ſometimes of <hi>one</hi> Angell vnto <hi>one</hi> man too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.1. We reade that Iacob ſawe a whole hoſte of Angells round about him. And 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaes</hi> ſervant ſawe the mountaynes full of horſes and fier; full of Angells, about the Prophet.</p>
            <p>Againe. We read that an Angell, in the <hi>ſingular</hi> was ſent to deliuer all Iſraell (and they were <hi>plurall</hi>) out of Egipt. And at the ſeige of Ieruſalem by Senacherib, God ſent an Angell that ſlew 185000. of the <hi>Aſsirians</hi> their enemyes in one night.</p>
            <p>And againe it is not improbable that vnto every one man their is ſome one particular Angell (<hi>pro certo aſſerrere non Auſum,</hi> ſo Calvin, <hi>ſententiam magis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem dicit</hi> Zanchius <hi>Aquinas noſter reformatus</hi>) it is not I ſay improbable but that vnto every particular man is aſſigned ſome particular Angell as his <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> and protector.</p>
            <p>Our ſaviour intimates thus much <hi>Math:</hi> 18.10: their Angells <hi>Diſtinctiue,</hi> ſo the fathers do expound it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould the face of my father which is in heaven. And when S. <hi>Peter</hi> (whom the diſciples thought to haue bin faſt enough in Herods priſon) came vnto the dore where they were aſſembled <hi>Act.</hi> 12.15. they ſayd that it was not Peter, but his Angell, and they <hi>ſpake</hi> doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe according to the opinion then commonlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved in the Church, The Evangeliſt relates it as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1216:8"/>of it. S. Peter did not after wards reproue them for it. The Iewes are of the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this day; &amp; ſo are all the auncient fathers of the Chriſtian Church, nor may we but give great reverence vnto their opinions in ſuch things as doe not opugne the rule of fayth, as this doth not.</p>
            <p>When as therefore wee cannot denye but that there are many, and muſt needs graunt that there is one An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell at the leaſt, aſſigned to attend, to defend, to protect thoſe that feare God.</p>
            <p>The moderne learned doe ſubſcribe vnto <hi>Zanchius</hi> his concluſion. That ther is one Angell ordinarily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned vnto every one man as a Tutor or protector of him in all his waies, <hi>via pueritiae, adoleſcentiae, aetatis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilis, mortis, ab ovo ad malum</hi> even from his birth vnto his death. but for our greater confort, as it fared ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> when many enemies doe bandie themſelues againſt vs, we muſt beleiue (if wee feare him as they did) God will ſend whole legions and Hoſtes of Angells to aſſiſt vs. But becauſe God is moſt mercifull and therefore willing, and Almighty and therfore able of himſelfe without any ſuch inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat encamping of Angells to preſerue them that feare him: Nor are wee to multiply entityes without neceſſitye: This doctrine may peradventure ſeeme to be ſuperfluous; we propoſed therefore to anſwere this obiection in the laſt place, which wee doe endeauor. thus.</p>
            <p>Agents ſubordinate, we ſay, may well concurre in the working of one and the ſame effect. 'Tis God wee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1216:8"/>graunt that doth protect vs <hi>ratione g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ber nationis,</hi> but by his Angells he doth protect vs <hi>ratione executionis,</hi> as the Fathers ſpeake.</p>
            <p>For looke into my text and it tells you not ſimplie of any Angell, but of the Angells of the Lord, with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, for the Angells performe not this office vnto vs, but as they are ſent and enabled for this cauſe from God. They encampe not of themſelues but where their emperour commandeth them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Agens per mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt minus efficax in agendo,</hi> you may tell me that an agent working by ſome intermediate meanes and not immediatly or by it ſelfe is leſſe power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the effect. <hi>Sivtatur medio propter neceſsitatem.</hi> 'Tis true (we ſay) if he doe vſe that meanes as of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie; But the omnipotency of God needeth not therein the miniſtrie of Angells. God by his power can of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe protect his ſeruants without the meanes of any of his Creatures, he can arme the meaneſt of them with ſufficient ſtrenght to free them from the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</p>
            <p n="1">1 But to expreſſe his ſingular loue, his favour, and care over them that feare him, Angells muſt not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from this imployment.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is a glory and honour vnto them that they ſhould be imployed in their Creators ſervice.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It makes moreouer for the order and beautie of the world that things ſuperior leſſe ſubiect to mutation and to change ſhould gouerne and rule the inferior world more pliable to alterations. I will heare the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſaith God <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 2.22. and the heauens ſhall heare the earth</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1216:9"/>
               <hi>Aſtra regunt homines &amp; regit aſtra Deus.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>The ſtarres rule men and God rules them.</q>
            <p>And againe for our comfort when peradventure (as Iacob travailing to Haran) we are deſolate and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourleſſe, forſaken and left of all, yet open we but then the eie of faith, and wee ſhall ſee as he did, the Angells of God aſcending, and deſcending, as ready to goe, and to returne with vs, and God himſelfe ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboue the ladder,<note place="margin">Luke. 12.7. Luk. 21.18.</note> by whoſe guidance the courſe of all our life is ordered to a <hi>haire;</hi> for they are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and not one of them can fall without his privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and knowledge.</p>
            <p>This of the Angell protecting. The 2. particuler in the firſt generall, concernes, the manner how the Angells doe protect vs, and that is by <hi>encamping them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,</hi> and that <hi>round about vs,</hi> as my text ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>This their <hi>caſtrametation,</hi> their encamping, or pitch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of their tents about vs, muſt needs implie, that there are enemies alwaies ready to aſſault vs and that the holy Angells are alwaies ready to defend vs, and that our life is but <hi>militia</hi> a warefare vpon earth.</p>
            <p>The Devill as a roaring lion goes about night and daie ſeeking whom he may devour.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> And the Angell of the Lord (ſaith my text) <hi>encampeth, round about them that feare him,</hi> the devill cannot harme them, for the Angells doe excell in ſtrength. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 103.</p>
            <p>Seven Devills may aſſault thee; aſwell as Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen, yet feare them not, feare God, and his Angell ſhall giue thee deliuerance from them. <hi>Magna ſatanae potentia eſt, ſed ſub Dei omnipotentia eſt.</hi> For behold
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1216:9"/>they are bound and they are bound, in chaines, ſo that they may not doe all that they can doe, neither can they doe, all that they would doe,<note place="margin">Iob. 26.</note> 
               <hi>facit quod potest Diabolus Deo permittente, quod poteſt non facit deo prohibente.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſhall wee ſtand ſtill, and bee ſpectators only,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26. Gal. 1.2. 2. Cor. 5.20. 1. Cor. 1.30.</note> whileſt the Angells doe thus beſtirre themſelues about vs? He who made vs by his owne power, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs by his owne moſt precious blood, and iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vs by his owne free grace; he will not ſaue vs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our owne good workes, <hi>Deus vult hoc eſse propter hoc, ſed non propter hoc vult hoc eſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt arme our ſelues, <hi>put on the whole armor of God,</hi> as it is deſcribed <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 6. and being armed, wee muſt not flie, but ſtand to it, ſtand ſtedfaſt in the faith we muſt, and we muſt not ſtand idle, noe, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Diuill <hi>Iames.</hi> 4.7. and then ſhall the Angell of the Lord aſſiſt vs, and God himſelfe (the fight being ended) crowne vs, <hi>vincenti dabitur Corona.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This of the manner how they protect vs. The 3. thing we propoſed to intreate of, is who they are that are protected by the Angells, Thoſe are they that <hi>feare God</hi> as my text ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>There is a filiall, and a ſervile feare, the one is the guift of the ſpirit, ariſing from the loue of God, the other is of our owne corrupted nature, ariſing from the guilt of ſinne. The one reſpecteth or looketh vpon God, as a Father, the other as a judge, a good man feareth to offend God, and a bad man when he hath offended feareth to be puniſhed of God. The Angell
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1216:10"/>of the Lord encamping round about them that feare him, bidds vs not feare him with any ſervill feare, for they encampe themſelves about vs for our deliverance from evills. But that ſame filiall feare, muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in all them about whom the Angells may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe themſelues. <hi>The Angell of the Lord</hi> therefore (ſaith my text) encampeth round about them that ſcare him.</p>
            <p>Here, the ſchooles diſpute 1. whether thoſe that doe not feare God, haue not their Angells to protect them, &amp; againe whether thoſe that doe feare God, are alwaies attended by their Angells.</p>
            <p>To the 1. they anſwere, that the wicked, thoſe that are moſt wicked, and they doe inſtance even in Anti-Chriſt himſelfe, haue notwithſtanding their Angell Guardians with them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To with-hould their malice, that they become not ſo extreamely wicked, and evill, as otherwiſe they would be. 2. in curbing or bridling in, the power of the Divill, that he doth not inſtantly as they for their wickedneſſe deſerue, and he for his malice doth deſire deſtroy them. But were it ſo, yet we ſhall find, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this protection of the wicked by the Angells doth moſt ſtrongly reflect vpon the Godly.</p>
            <p>For doubtleſſe, it cannot be ſuppoſed, that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the wicked is reſtrayned, that they ſhould not be wicked, but that they by their wickedneſſe ſhould not too much annoye the elect of God. Did the Angell doe you thinke, keepe Balaam that he ſhould not curſe Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, becauſe he ſhould not curſe? no it was becauſe he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1216:10"/>ſhould not curſe Iſrael only. Nor is it againe for their owne ſake, that the Divill hath not at all times power to confound the wicked. No, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſeth God to continue them, as he did the Cananites in Iſrael, to exerciſe the patience of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.10.</note> and for the greater glory which ſhall be giuen vnto them that overcome.</p>
            <p>The 2. doubt reſpects thoſe that doe feare God themſelues, for whereas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the beſt of man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not once but ſeauen times, not in a yeere, but in a day, ſo that the feare of God is not alwaies before their eies, <hi>quoad actum,</hi> who yet <hi>quoad habitum</hi> wee cannot ſay but that they doe feare God. The queſtion is, whether at ſuch times, the Angells doe ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, or elſe, forgoe their charge.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They doe never leaue to preſerue our life from the malice of the Divill, and from thoſe many caſuall dangers, wee are daiely ſubiect to, and every man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, hath had often experience of.</p>
            <p>But ſometimes, it pleaſeth God to withdraw them from vs: ſo that we fall then, either <hi>in malum Culpae</hi> by ſinne, or <hi>in malum poenae</hi> for ſinne; then they doe <hi>leaue</hi> vs, but they doe not then <hi>forſake</hi> vs.</p>
            <p>They ſtand aloofe of, when we fall, but preſently they come in againe to take vs vp. When we ſinne, they are at hand, to moue vs to repentance; for though they hate our ſinnes, yet they doe loue our ſoules; Nor can the divills malice be ſo intenſe to harme vs, as is their loue to helpe vs. Night and day he travaileth, to effect his ends and the holye Angells, doe continually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1216:11"/>themſelfes about vs, to defend vs from them. <hi>The Angell of the Lordenca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peth,</hi> as noting a pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rpetuall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for our delivera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from them. And that is the laſt thing we propoſed to intreat of.</p>
            <p>This deliverance, which Gods holy Angells doe afford vnto vs, reſpecteth either the <hi>body,</hi> or the <hi>ſoule.</hi> For the <hi>body,</hi> we read that they doe fight for vs, and drive our enemyes backe from vs <hi>Apoc:</hi> 12.7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.19.</p>
            <p>Somtimes againe, by way of <hi>reſcue,</hi> they take vs from them, when we are overtaken with them; ſo did they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> out of <hi>Priſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes, as <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions denne, and the three Children in the fierie fornace, they doe <hi>preſerve</hi> vs from evill, although wee live even in the mideſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills. The one was preſerved from the power of the Lions, though in the Lions denne. The other from the power of the fire, though in a firie ſurnace. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tims as they dealt with <hi>Theodorus</hi> in <hi>Socrates,</hi> (of whom you may reade alſo in Theodoret,) and S. <hi>Paule</hi> in the perill of ſhipwracke, and Iacob in his going and returne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> they are with vs in trouble to comfort and to aſſiſt vs. <hi>Theodorus</hi> though he ſweat for it If that ſame ſweat be wiped of with an Angells hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercheif, will ſeeme rather a pleaſure then a paine vnto him. So for the body. As for the ſoule they doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the will <hi>mediante illuminatione,</hi> by illumining the minde, and that <hi>mediante phantaſia</hi> by ſuggeſting good thoughts, and wholſome councells, <hi>ſuggerunt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non ingerunt, hortantur ad bonum non creant</hi> ſo they inſtructed <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.15. the Apoſtles <hi>Acts.</hi> Dainel. 1.10. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohn <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.10.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1216:11"/>
            <p>And ſometimes againe though not immediatlye and by themſelues,<note place="margin">Soc. l. 20. c. 19. Theod l. 3.19.</note> yet by the miniſtrie of men they deale thus kindely with vs for our ſoules health.</p>
            <p>It was an Angell that did ſend <hi>Philip</hi> to inſtruct <hi>Candaces Eunuch Acts.</hi> 8. It was an Angell that adviſed <hi>Cornelius</hi> to ſend for <hi>Peter</hi> to preach vnto him <hi>Acts.</hi> 10. It was their Angell, (ſo the text tells vs) that called forth <hi>Paul</hi> to preach the goſpell in <hi>Macedonia Acts.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>So is God good vnto vs thus to ordaine ſuch noble and excellent creatures to attend vppon vs, creatures ſpirituall to attend on mortall, innocent on ſinfull, the moſt glorious and excellent creatures vpon men made of no better mold then duſt.</p>
            <p>They doe attende vpon vs, and they doe ſee all our moſt ſecrete actions: <hi>tu autem audes illo Angelo custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de preſente, quod me preſente non auderes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As they reioyce at our weldoings, ſo are they ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeved at out ſinnes, <hi>tanquam Apes fumo,</hi> as bees by ſmoake, ſo are they driven from vs by them.</p>
            <p>When we will not attende their holy councells, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradict &amp; thwart their good adviſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, then when they cannot further vs in good: Their whole endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (as before I ſayd) is that we become not ſo extrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked as of our ſelues without them we ſhould be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord what is man,</hi> ADAM <hi>made of earth that thou art thus mindfull of him or</hi> ENOSH <hi>the miſerable ſonne of man that thou ſo regardeſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To God be Glorye. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
